בוקר טוב, Boker tov,
good ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, first day of אייר, Iyar, sixteenth day
of the עומר. Omer. We pick up with a new פרק perek
today. So the דף daf is נ״ט Nun Tet 59. We pick
up at the bottom of נ״ח עמוד ב׳, Nun Chet Amud Bet,
the beginning of the third פרק, perek, and let's get it started.
האומר לחבירו
צא וקדש לי אשה:
ha'omer l'chaveiro
tzei v'kadesh li ishah: a man says to his friend, go marry
a woman for me. והלך וקידשה לעצמו: v'halach v'kidshah l'atzmo: and this
guy went and found a wonderful woman and then decided, why am
I marrying her to my friend? So he decided to marry her
himself. Who was that the story about? Miles Standish or something?
The Courtship of Miles Standish?
Was that the story? I think so. Yeah. All right anyway, wasn't
it one of those stories also about the founding fathers or
something about, no? Am I anyway... all right anyway okay.
So rather than going ahead...
I don't know about that.
All right anyway, they had a lot more they were...
okay anyway, not I mean the founding fathers, I meant like the
pilgrims. Wasn't there a pilgrim story about that? About anyway whatever. All
right anyway, והלך וקידשה לעצמו מקודשת לשני. v'halach v'kidshah l'atzmo mekudeshet lashaini.
She's married to the second guy. Now תוספות Tosafot of course says
like, okay, what's the חידוש? chiddush? I mean it might not have
been a nice thing to do, you agreed to marry her to
the guy who sent you and you married her for
yourself, but what's the הלכה halachic חידוש chiddush here? So if you
look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says והלך וקידשה לעצמו מקודשת. v'halach
v'kidshah l'atzmo mekudeshet.
So תוספות Tosafot says ואם תאמר מה חידוש יש כאן פשיטא, v'im
tomar mah chiddush yesh kan p'shita, of course. ויש לומר דמהיכא דאמר
השליח להאשה בשעת הקידושין, v'yesh lomar d'maicha d'amar hashaliach l'isha b'sha'at hakidushin,
he said at the moment of marriage,
פלוני
שלחני לקדשך לו, Ploni shlachani l'kadeshach lo, so-and-so sent me to marry
you off to him. ובתוך כך אמר לה, u'vetoch kach amar lah,
and then he said to her, הרי את מקודשת לי. harei at
mekudeshet li.
Like every rabbi under the חופה.
chuppah. Right. והיא ידעה דלנפשיה קאמר. v'hi yada'at d'l'nafshei ka'amar. She couldn't
have been confused. If she thought that when he said לי, li,
he meant in the voice of the משלח, meshaleach, then it would
have been a קידושי טעות. kidushei ta'ut. But she realized he meant
to himself. דאי לאו הכי לא הויא מקודשת. d'ei lav hachi lo
havya mekudeshet. Otherwise it wouldn't work. Okay, then what's the חידוש? chiddush?
He said הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet li, she understood
that he meant to him, to the guy who was standing in
front of her. והשמיענו חידוש דמהו דתימא, v'hishmi'anu chiddush d'mahu d'teima, nevertheless
I might have thought, עד דכאמר לי לצורך משלחו קאמר, ad d'ka'amar
li l'tzorech mishlacho ka'amar, that maybe when he says לי li he's
speaking in the voice of the משלח meshaleach and therefore I guess
she wouldn't be married to either, because the woman wanted to marry
the guy in front of her, but maybe the לי li here
meant the משלח, meshaleach, not me. קא משמע לן דלא, ka mashma
lan d'lo, we don't say that. So it's cute because it raises
the question of when you're representing the person who sent you, when
you say לי, li, me, you know, you're still speaking then in
your own voice, you're not speaking in the voice of the person
who sent you.
But anyway תוספות Tosafot specifies והיא ידעה, v'hi yada'at, right. But generally
what we're doing is we're interpreting objectively.
Right, like why don't we just say דברים שבלב אינם דברים? dvarim
shebalev einam dvarim? Right, yeah.
That's what we always do. We never say what did she think
he meant. We always say what this language means or whatever the
situation.
Right. Right, it's a good point. You know, so would we have
had a הוה אמינא hava amina that even if she were not
ידעה yada'at that objectively... but I guess it's objectively ambiguous, well yeah,
I don't know. It's a good question. It's a good question. Anyway,
so the חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishnah is, right, that
I don't know what the חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishnah is,
but the case of the משנה Mishnah is that even though the
guy decided to marry her to himself, she's married to that guy
who married her. וכן האומר לאשה, v'chein ha'omer l'isha, and וכן v'chein
is also interesting, what exactly the comparison is. A woman, האומר לאשה
הרי את מקודשת לי לאחר שלשים יום, ha'omer l'isha harei at mekudeshet
li l'achar shloshim yom, you're married to me after thirty days. ובא
אחר וקידשה, u'va acher v'kidshah, and somebody else married her before the
thirty days arrived, the thirtieth day arrived.
בתוך שלשים יום, betoch shloshim yom, מקודשת לשני. mekudeshet lashaini. She's married
to the second. So the comparison is somebody jumped in. So maybe
the point of the משנה Mishnah is the same way in the
first case it's obvious that even though the first guy sent him,
the second guy married her to himself, obviously that works. Here too,
even though the first guy started the process, did the act that
would take effect, nevertheless it hasn't taken effect yet, and if somebody
jumps in and marries her before that thing takes effect, it works
to the second guy.
בת ישראל לכהן תאכל בתרומה. bat Yisrael l'Kohen tochal b'terumah. And if
the second guy is a כהן, Kohen, she's fully married to the
second guy.
Give back the ring? Yeah, she would have to give back the
ring. That's true. And maybe to some degree that's the question earlier
in the גמרא Gemara about מעות מתנה ma'ot matanah or מעות פקדון
ma'ot pikadon or whatever, but yes, she would have to give back
the ring to the first guy. מעכשיו ולאחר שלשים יום. me'achshav v'l'achar
shloshim yom. If it's as of now and completing in thirty days,
and we'll see what that might mean. So... בא וקידשה בתוך שלשים
יום, ba ve-kiddeshtah be-tokh sheloshim yom, somebody that tried to marry her
within these thirty days, מקודשת ואינה מקודשת. mekuddeshet ve-eina mekuddeshet. So she's
questionably married to the second guy. When the first guy said as
of now, how much is that going to make it all retroactive
from the first moment? Or how much is it all still going
to be pushed off to the end? Or maybe it's some type
of an interim status. So whether she can be married, whether the
marriage to the second guy works or not is unclear. בת ישראל
לכהן או בת כהן לישראל, bat Yisrael le-kohen o bat kohen le-Yisrael,
if either she's if the second guy's a כהן kohen or if
she's the daughter of a כהן kohen and the second guy's a
ישראל, Yisrael,
so in either case, לא תאכל בתרומה, lo tokhal bi-trumah, she can't
eat תרומה. trumah. Meaning if she's a בת ישראל bat Yisrael married
to and the second guy's a כהן, kohen, she can't eat תרומה
trumah because she might not be married to the second guy. If
she's a בת כהן bat kohen and the second guy is a
ישראל, Yisrael, then she also can't eat תרומה trumah because she might
be married to the second guy. So either way, it's a way
of illustrating that we don't know whether she is you know how
confident we are that she's married to the second guy. Yes.
Small question today: what's this about the תרומה? trumah? Like she's sleeping...
we're talking about אשת איש, eshet ish, right? Since she's married to
one, she can't sleep with the other?
Right.
Well, yeah, I mean I think that the point is that the
תאכל בתרומה tokhal bi-trumah is a way to test even in the
interim. Let me think about that. Meaning if you look
at if you think about the first case, the first case is
when he said לאחר שלשים יום le-achar sheloshim yom and then the
second guy married her within the thirty days and she can eat
תרומה trumah because she's married to the second guy, so if it's
obvious she's not married to the first guy because the thirty days
aren't up. And to say she can sleep with the second guy,
like, you know, I mean then that gets raising questions about what's
the איסור issur of sex outside of marriage and so on. So
I mean the תאכל בתרומה tokhal bi-trumah at least in the first
case is an indication, you know...
Not the question of sex outside of marriage, but that when you're
married to somebody now and you're sleeping with somebody else?
Right, but I'm right, I understand that. I think that that's more
true about the second case. If that's more that's more that that
you didn't have to use תרומה trumah to illustrate her questionable status
because the most obvious way of illustrating the questionable status in the
second case was she can't have sex with either guy because she
might be married to the other one, right? You're right. That's true
in the second case. The first case you understand a little bit
more why they gave the תרומה trumah because it's more obvious she's
not married to the first guy and it's a way of testing
if she's married to the second. But you're right, by the second
case it's like she can't sleep with either one because it might
be אשת איש. eshet ish. Yeah, Charlie?
Why wouldn't she sleep with either one, she's an ארוסה, arusah, she's
not an...
alright, fine. But it wouldn't be אשת איש. eshet ish. Yes.
I would have thought the חידוש chiddush in the רישא reisha was
that if I'm someone's, I guess this is not true, if I'm
your שליח, shaliach, I can't speak in my own voice. In other
words, everything I say is, is that not true?
No. What are you saying? You make me your שליח shaliach and
I go ahead and I decide I want to buy some groceries.
I'm buying groceries for you? I mean, no.
No. I mean if a פועל poel can be חוזר בחצי היום,
chozer be-chatzi ha-yom, a שליח shaliach can also be חוזר בחצי היום,
chozer be-chatzi ha-yom, you know. You can give up your you know
you can renounce your שליחות shelichut at any time. Alright. האומר לחברו.
ha-omer le-chavero. So now we're going to deal with the more with
the sort of the you know the moral aspect of the first
case because legally it works, right? The guy the שליח shaliach decided
to act on his own behalf, but is it the right thing
to do or not?
So
תנו רבנן, tnu rabanan, we learned a ברייתא. braita. מה שעשה עשוי,
mah she-asah asui, fine, it works that the woman is married to
the to the agent. But אלא שנהג בה מנהג רמאות. ela she-nahag
bah minhag rama'ut. He was he was a scoundrel, he was a
you know he acted in a deceptive way to the first guy.
He told the first guy he would do this for him and
then the woman that the first guy maybe wanted to marry, he
took for himself. Now I do have to question because this is
sort of going to be running through this, but I want to
put it out there that you know, if the first guy said
here's the specific woman I want you to marry for me, right?
And you know then you really understand like he stole the woman
from under this guy's nose, right? But let's say he just says
find me a nice woman to marry for me. And this guy
goes and he goes to the town, he's looking around and he
sees this wonderful woman that he decides he wants to marry herself
and the woman agrees, right? Is that such a terrible thing? I
mean you know like it's hard to imagine like like also I
think because we're talking not just about like find me a nice
car, you know or whatever. Talking about somebody's like sort of a
life choice about a life partner, right? So if you find and
I don't know like I mean it does raise
interesting questions which is like if the first guy and the woman
had already been like engaged and in conversation and this guy's coming,
it's one thing, right? But you know in the realities the גמרא's
Gemara talking about, is it clear that the that the first guy
and the woman had been engaged? Maybe he just says oh I've
seen this woman she seems wonderful see if you can talk her
into getting married to me. And this guy decides I'm going to
marry, you know... אשה פלונית, isha plonit, right? What? Well it's not
clear what the case is. אשה פלונית, isha plonit, right? The משנה,
Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah says אשה פלונית. isha plonit. That's true, very
good point. Yes, I think I had skipped over that. Right. So
if it's like a specific woman, right? So then I think you
know you understand a little bit more. Look, even if it is
a specific woman, I mean I think it raises interesting questions which
is like if the first guy and the woman had already been...
Number one is how much was there already a like, you know,
a not just the a desire on the part of the first
guy, but an actual connection to this woman that a, you know,
and an engagement of whether I don't mean necessarily they're engaged, but
they were already, you know, had developed a relationship that this guy
was coming to intervene with, you know, is one question. If there
hadn't been really an existing relationship, one wonders how bad it is.
And the other thing is is the fact that this is about
a choice about the person you're going to spend your life with,
you know? So I mean, I don't know. I guess in my
mind it raises questions about, you know, about those about about like
when is it justified to do it that way.
And also like, I mean, sometimes the גמרא Gemara speaks of this
totally as just a financial transaction. Right. And sometimes it's more of
a, you know, a choice of the people involved. Right.
So I think that that's true. We're going to compare it very
soon to questions about like buying a piece of property. Okay, which
is a different story. I mean, maybe the reason the גמרא Gemara
isn't raising the issues I'm raising is cause, you know, the גמרא
Gemara was in a time where it was not so much about
romantic marriage, right? But I'm putting it out there. Let's keep on
reading the גמרא Gemara and see. But I think the fact that
it started with a concrete woman is an important point and again,
whether they already had a concrete relationship, that, you know, or the
guy just saw this woman from afar, you know, I think is
an interesting question as well.
All's fair in love and war. Right, exactly. And that that's probably
based on, you know, the this is not an unusual, I mean,
it's not and
in one way, but in
another way, yes, it's not so unusual. Right. And look, the גמרא
Gemara talks about the you know you're allowed to do קידושין kiddushin
even like on, you know, תשעה באב Tisha B'Av because of שמא
יקדמנו אחר. shema yekadmenu acher.
Maybe somebody else will beat you, you know, you know, you know,
will beat you to it. So, now that wasn't the case where
you sent the guy to do it, right? So the guy agreed
to act on your behalf and then he switched and acted on
his own behalf. You didn't send him, then everybody's always acting on
their own behalf and you understand, you know, it's like may the
best man win, you know? But right, here it's a little different,
but even here, I do, anyway, I raise the question based on
the circumstances, like when would it be appropriate.
And also, as Doug was saying, I mean, in this kind of
situation, you have to think about what that woman's desire is also.
Right. I mean, if she's willing to switch, maybe she, I guess
that question of love if they don't consider love I guess.
Yeah, I mean, but that we know that that happens too, you
know, this courtship and whatever and somebody gets, you know, was thinking
about whatever and then yeah, so he meets somebody else. Right, exactly.
Exactly. Okay, אמר ליה לחבירו. Amar lei l'chavero. Okay, תנא מה שעשה
עשוי אלא שנהג בו מנהג רמאות.
Tana
mah
she'asah asuy ela shenahag bo minhag rammut.
והתנא דידן V'hatanna didan
and how about our תנא tanna who did not mention the moral
critique? Sort of... הלך נמי דקתני הלך ברמאות. Halach nami d'katani halach
b'rammut. Now when it says and he went, הלך
וקדשה לעצמו. Halach v'kidshah l'atzmo.
It doesn't just say קדשה לעצמו, kidshah l'atzmo, it's it's the word
is coming to, you know, connote the idea that he went and
he did something dastardly. He went off, you know, and he married
her to himself, you know? So it's indicating that he did the
wrong thing. Okay, ומאי שנא הכא דקתני האומר לחבירו? U'mai shena hacha
d'katani ha'omer l'chavero? Now why does it say somebody who said to
his friend? ומאי שנא התם U'mai shena hatam
way back earlier it said, well not so much back, האומר לשלוחו
Ha'omer lishlucho
that if it said last פרק perek it said that if somebody
says to his שליח, shaliach, his agent, "Go marry this woman in
such and such a place," and he married her in another place,
it doesn't work. Okay, so why in one place does it describe
the guy you're sending as your friend and in the other guy
the other place as your שליח? shaliach? So הכא רבותא קמשמע לן
והתם רבותא קמשמע לן. Hacha revuta kamashma lan v'hatam revuta kamashma lan.
Each one is telling you a חידוש. chiddush. הכא רבותא קמשמע לן,
Hacha revuta kamashma lan, here it's telling you a חידוש chiddush דאי
תנא שלוחו, d'ee tana shlucho, if it had been that if you
had sent your agent, הוה אמינה שליח הוא דהוי רמאי. havah aminah
shaliach hu d'havay rammai.
It's only by the case of your agent the guy is considered
to be doing acting in a deceitful way. דסמכא דעתיה סבר עביד
לשליחותי. D'samcha datei savar avid lishlichuti.
Because you rely on him. You say, "I made him my agent,
he'll take care of it," you don't feel that you have to,
you know, be, you know, you feel that you've sufficiently delegated the
responsibility, it's no longer, you know, and you can be confident that
it's going to take place. אבל חבירו, Aval chavero, but if you
just asked your friend and not your agent, I have to say
I don't exactly understand the difference between agent and friend, right? Either
way, the guy halachically is your שליח, shaliach, you're empowering him to
do the act. But presumably, you know, one is that, I don't
know, maybe you paid him, you're in some type of an official
capacity, okay, or it was clear from the context that you were
saying like, "You do it for me and you take care of
this woman," as opposed to the other it's like, "Do me a
favor if you get the chance to," okay? So anyway, so in
the case to the friend, and that's the way רש"י Rashi says.
If you look at רש"י, Rashi, the last the fourth of the
lines from the top, he says חבירו שלא שלחו לשם כך אלא
אם יזדמן לו במקום פלוני דרך אצלה. Chavero shelo shlacho l'shem kach
ela im yizdamen lo b'makom ploni derech etzlah. If you happened to,
you know, oh, you're going to I hear you're going to, you
know, Cincinnati, if you happen to see this woman, you know, marry
her for me. It wasn't that you I sent you on a
mission. to do it, okay? So in that case where somehow you're
you're not in my employ or I didn't send you on a
mission, I asked you more to do me a favor if you
get a chance. So in that type of a case
הסברא חבירו דלא סמכא דעתיה, hasvara chaveiro delo samcha daiteih, I'm not
sure you're going to get a chance to do it. אימא לא
ליהוי רמאי, eima lo lehava ramai, then maybe you wouldn't be a
רמאי. ramai. השתא, hasta, nevertheless, our משנה mishna is telling you that
it's still the wrong thing to do. The irony being that it's
saying it's saying it in the משנה mishna to tell you it's
a רמאי, ramai, but the critique of רמאי ramai is not really
in the משנה. mishna. We're sort of reading it into the word
הלך, halach, which meant and he sneakingly went, but that's not actually
in the משנה. mishna. But anyway, that's the point, that even if
you're just asking a favor from your friend, it's the wrong thing
to do. By the way, you certainly also understand that from a
moral perspective, right? That if you sort of give me the responsibility
of doing it, then I'm really like sort of like reneging on
my obligation to you and in my own interest. As opposed to
ask to do you a favor, there's less of a sense of
a real commitment and obligation that I have to you.
And you said something that I never never occurred to me. In
a normal case of שליחות, shlichus, am I assuming that the משלח
meshaleach is paying the שליח? shaliach?
I normally assume
not. But it could be you are.
He said that in there,
so it could be you are. Why not? I mean, why should
I go to all this trouble for you? Exactly right. So yeah,
could be a it could be being paid, but that's not important
הלכתית halachically to the status of שליחות. shlichus. Okay,
so even if it was just a favor though, there's an element
of רמאות. rama'us. But again, I think that the point whoever pointed
it out that the משנה mishna explicitly says איש פלוני ish ploni
is relevant for that.
Exactly. You have more responsibility you feel exactly.
If you're sent on a mission, you're being paid to do that,
you're being contractually bound to it. Right. So obviously
there's more sense of betrayal when you actually choose to reverse it
there. Okay.
Okay. Now והשתא רבותא קמשמע לן, vehashta revuta kamashma lan, there when
you said it says you say to your שליח shaliach marry me
this woman in a particular place and she does he does it
in another place, it doesn't work. It's a חידוש chiddush that even
in the case of שליחות. shlichus. דאי תנא אמר לחבירו, de'i tana
amar lachaveiro, that you said to your friend, oh, if you happen
to be there, go marry this woman for me in that place.
הוה אמינא חבירו דכי קידשה במקום אחר אינה מקודשת. hava amina chaveiro
dechi kidsha bimkom acher aina mekudeshes. There I meant only that place
because I heard you were going to Cincinnati, so I meant in
Cincinnati marry her. וסבר לא טרח, vesavar lo tarach, I think that
and it doesn't even occur to me that you'll go looking for
her in another place. So I only made you a שליח shaliach
in Cincinnati, and therefore if it's another place it doesn't work. אלא
שלוחו, ela shlucho, but when I send you on a mission and
I say I'm hiring you, whatever, go to Cincinnati to find that
woman. So therefore you're taking the responsibility to do the effort on
my behalf,
לטרח, letarach, putting the effort on my behalf, אימא מראה מקום הוא
לו, eima mareh makom hu lo, maybe there basically I have to
go when you say Cincinnati you're just trying to
help
me out to let me know where I can find her, but
if you're sending me on a mission, I have to go ahead
and look for her wherever I might find her.
קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, not that way. That if you told me
that location, anything other than that location is not my שליחות shlichus
and even if I did it, it would not work. Okay. So
that's what's interesting about different scenarios where legally in all those cases
the person is empowered, he's given the, which what we would call
the
שליח, shaliach, he's given the legal power to do the act, but
in one case you're doing a favor, in the other case you're
being sent to do it, and what that might how that might
sort of change some of the context. Whether it's the sort of
moral aspect of it or whether it's other types of how we
interpret the words,
the context might change based on the nature of that relationship.
This might this might be מיישב meyashev the earlier מחלוקת machlokes about
מראה מקום mareh makom or קפדה. kapdah. Now you had to be
קפדה. kapdah.
Well, yes, that was the פסק psak of that משנה. mishna. And
the גמרא Gemara here is saying that the context, at least these
aspects of context wouldn't make a difference in terms of that. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara gets back to the issue of רמאות rama'us
and speaks about something that I think is less
sort of not the same sort of a consequence in terms of
who's going to be your life partner. So let's take a look.
רבין חסידא, Rabin Chasida, so the Rabin the righteous one, אזל לקדושי
ליה איתתא איתתא לברה, azal lekadoshei lei itata itata levrei, went to
marry a woman off to his for his son. His son obviously
had made him a שליח. shaliach. תוספות Tosafot deals with the problem
that the גמרא Gemara said earlier that a somebody is not חוצפהדיק
chutzpadik enough to ask your father to be a שליח shaliach to
marry a woman for her. So תוספות Tosafot well, maybe the father
suggested it to the son and the son liked the idea. Anyway
he's going to marry this woman off to his son. קידשה לנפשיה,
kidshah lenafshieh, but then when he actually started engaging the woman in
conversation he decided you know what, I'm going to marry her for
myself. Okay, so that's exactly going against the ברייתא braita at least.
So and this was and this was רבין חסידא. Rabin Chasida. I'm
assuming חסידא Chasida wasn't just a last name. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says דתניא, detanya, but don't we teach in a ברייתא braita
מה שעשה עשוי אלא שנהג מנהג רמאות, mah she'asah asuy ela shenahag
minhag rama'us, that it's an act of like deception,
betrayal. So the גמרא Gemara says no, לא יהבו ניהלה. lo yehavu
neihalah. No, the story was was that they were refusing to marry
this daughter off to his son because his son wasn't חשוב hashuv
enough for her to marry her. Oh, you want to marry her
for yourself? Oh, that's a good idea. By the way, notice that
it's the, you know, she, the woman here is, it doesn't have
a voice. It's clearly the family. They did not give her to
him. You know, they would not give her over to the son,
but they would be happy to marry her off to the father.
He was a much more חשוב hashuv person. So the גמרא Gemara
says nevertheless, איבעי ליה לאודועי, ibaya lei la-aduyei, which is a very
interesting insight. Like even if it's okay, right, because it's not like,
it's not like, you know, you're taking this woman away from your
son because they're not going to give her to your son, but
nevertheless you should first tell your son what you're doing. You should
send back a message. Because if you don't, right, the experience is
one of being betrayed. Right, if you let people know, which is
very powerful, right, if you let people know what's happening, let me
explain to you this or whatever, they wouldn't, I want, you know,
I'm planning on doing it myself, you know, then they, they might
not be happy, but they understand the reality, right? And in the
case where they just find out, it's what?! You made it for
yourself and not for me?! Right, even if the explanation comes later,
there's certainly an experience of being betrayed, right, when that happens without
letting the person know, the person who asked you to do it,
informing that person about what the reality is and why it's not
going to be happening. Okay, so you should have informed.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no. סבר אדהכי והכי אתי איניש אחריני
ומקדש לה. savar ad hacha ve-hacha ati inish achrini mekadesh lah. There's
the שמא יקדמנו אחר. shema yikdemenu acher. By the time it takes
me to send a message back to my son and inform him,
and maybe I want to hear if he's okay with it, right,
maybe that's also, but anyway, but by the time that, that takes
me, somebody else, this obviously woman was obviously very desired by others,
you know, and therefore, he was afraid he would lose the opportunity.
All right, so in that case it was seen as okay. So
here's this idea that like it's such an important opportunity, you know,
you don't want to ruin it is seen as acceptable when at
least, you know, you've tried to do the right thing otherwise or
when at least, you know, but, you know, if there's an opportunity
to make it more right, you need to make it more right.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבה בר
בר חנה יהב ליה זוזי לרב. Rabbah bar bar Chana yeiv lei
zuzei le-Rav. So now there's another story. Now we switch from marrying
a woman to buying land. רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar
Chana gave money to רב. Rav. אמר, amar, and he said to
him, זבנין לי האי ארעא. zavnin li hai ar'a. Go buy for
me this plot of land. אזל, azal, so רב Rav went, זבנה
לנפשיה. zavnah le-nafsheih. He bought it for himself. אה תניא מה שעשה
עשוי אלא שנהגו בו מנהג רמות? a tanya mah she-asah asuy ella
shene’agu bo minhag ramut? Ah, but don't we teach that that's deceptive?
And here the גמרא Gemara presumably is applying, you know, the, the
teaching here about marriage to other types of scenarios as well. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no.
באגא דאלימי הוה. baga d'alimei havah. That was a swamp or a
plot of land that was owned by some very, you know, sort
of strong-armed people, and לרב נהגי ביה כבוד, le-Rav nahagi beih kavod,
and they wouldn't necessarily sell it to anyone. For רב Rav they
were, they showed honor to רב Rav and they'd be prepared to
sell it to רב. Rav. לרבה בר בר חנה לא נהגי ביה
כבוד, le-Rabbah bar bar Chana lo nahagi beih kavod, but they wouldn't
have given that honor and they wouldn't have sold it to רבה
בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana who was the person who
had asked רב Rav to buy it. And presumably they wouldn't have
sold it to רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana even
on the request, you know, of רב. Rav. רב Rav was the,
they were only prepared to sell it to רב Rav himself. Similar
to the previous story. So the גמרא Gemara says nevertheless, איבעי ליה
לאודועי, ibaya lei la-aduyei, you should have told him, right, because if
you tell him then you can also see that, meaning before I
was sort of emphasizing that the point of telling is so that
the person doesn't feel betrayed when they find out. But there's another
aspect as well because when you tell them, you in a certain
way like formally end your שליחות, shelichus, you know, you're letting this
person know they won't sell it to me so I can no
longer sort of operate on your behalf in this, in this capacity
and then you go and you operate on your own behalf, right?
So you're sort of formally terminating your representing of that person, right,
as opposed to when you don't do it then there's much more
of a sense of you were supposed to be representing me and
you were going ahead and acting on your own behalf. So the
גמרא Gemara says, shouldn't he have informed, you know, רבה בר בר
חנה? Rabbah bar bar Chana? So the גמרא Gemara says, סבר אדהכי
והכי אתי איניש אחריני וזבין לה. savar ad hacha ve-hacha ati inish
achrini zavnin lah. No, he was afraid that in the time that
it would take to do that, somebody else would come and buy
the land. Clearly, just parallel to the previous story, this was like
hot property. Okay, so he had to seize the opportunity. רב גידל
הוה מהפך בההיא ארעא. Rav Giddel havah mahpeich behu ar'a. רב גידל
Rav Giddel was like trying to purchase a certain plot of land.
Literally מהפך mahpeich means like turning over, right, but he was in
negotiations, trying to purchase a plot of land.
We use the same phrase turning over. Yeah. Do we? I think
so, you turned it over to somebody else.
No, that's not what we mean. מהפך בה mahpeich bah means he
was like he was engaged in trying to purchase it. He was
engaged in negotiations about it. אזל רבי אבא זבנה. azal Rabbi Abba
zavnah. So רבי אבא Rabbi Abba went, now this was not a
שליח, shaliach, this was just somebody, this was like everybody for themselves,
right? So רבי אבא Rabbi Abba went and he purchased it. So
that's a different type of a question. So, and the גמרא Gemara
by the way by the case of marriage is not critical of
that. The גמרא Gemara speaks about שמא יקדמנו אחר, shema yikdemenu acher,
you know, you shouldn't wait, somebody else might beat you to it
or whatever and the גמרא Gemara usually is not critical. The גמרא
Gemara was only critical here. When you were supposed to be representing
the person. Okay? So anyway, רבי אבא Rabbi Abba went and he
bought the land. אתא רב גידל קבליה לרבי זירא. Ata Rav Gidel
kavlei leRabbi Zeira. So רב גידל Rav Gidel who was trying to
buy the land went and complained to רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira on
the actions of רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. אתא רבי זירא קבליה לרבי
יצחק נפחא. Atha Rabbi Zeira kavlei leRabbi Yitzchak Nafcha. רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira went and he knocked it up, he bumped it up, he
told רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha about this, about how רבי
אבא Rabbi Abba acted. אמר ליה Amar lei so רבי יצחק נפחא
Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha said to רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira המתין עד דאייל
גבנן לרגלא. hamtin ad de'ayeil gavnan lereigla. Wait until רבי אבא Rabbi
Abba comes to us for the רגל, regel, for יום טוב, Yom
Tov, you know, the big רש"י Rashi says, the big lectures that
they would give, you know, in the thirty days before the יום
טוב, Yom Tov, everybody would gather. So he's going to come to
those pre-יום טוב Yom Tov lectures, פירקא דירחא כלה pirka diyarcha kalla
and then I'll have a chance to see him and I'll talk
to him then. Okay. כי סליק, Ki salik, so when רבי אבא
Rabbi Abba went for those שיעורים shiurim and רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi
Yitzchak Nafcha saw him, אשכחיה, ashcheichei, רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha
found him. אמר ליה Amar lei he said to him,
so רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha said to רבי אבא, Rabbi
Abba, רבי אבא Rabbi Abba was the one who bought the land,
אמר ליה Amar lei עני המהפך בחררה, ani mehappech becharara, let's say
a poor person is trying to take possession of like a, you
know, of like a wafer, of a piece of cake, right? ובא
אחר ונטלה הימנו, Uva acher venatla heimenu, and somebody came and took
it under his nose. מאי, Mai, what's the הלכה? halacha? אמר ליה
Amar lei נקרא רשע, nikra rasha, the guy who stole it from
under his nose is a
רשע. rasha. Not stole it, but took it from under his nose.
So it says, אלא מר מאי טעמא עבד הכי, Ella mar mai
taama avad hachi, so why did you do what you did? So
like a דוד David and what a נתן הנביא Natan HaNavi type
of a story, first you give him another story where, look, isn't
that what you did? You stole this plot of land, or not
stole, but took it from under the nose of רב גידל? Rav
Gidel? I don't know, the מוכר mocher is everybody in
negotiations with the guy.
I don't think so. No, you kidding me? It's like whoever, well,
like I'm selling my house, you made me an offer, somebody else
makes me a better offer, it's like that's understood. That's business. Whoever
goes ahead and makes me the best offer, whatever's ready to buy
it right now.
You're still in the middle of
the negotiations, I didn't sign anything. Exactly. Okay, but you know, for
the בין אדם לחברו, bein adam lachaveiro, for me, I know, I'm
going to sell it to whoever's going to make me the best
offer. But from your perspective, what are you doing stealing, you know,
taking it out from under the nose of the person who was
about to buy
it? Okay. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said to him, לא
הוה ידענא, lo hava yadana, I didn't realize he was in negotiations.
Who knew? The seller didn't tell me, I saw a nice plot
of land, I didn't know that. So the גמרא Gemara says, השתא
נמי ניתני עלי מר. hashta nami niteini ali mar. So okay, fine,
you didn't know, that's great, so you want to do the right
thing, so go ahead and sell it to whoever it was, sell
it to רב גידל. Rav Gidel. אמר ליה Amar lei זבוני לא
מזבנינא ליה, zemunei lo mizabnina lei, look,
I'm not going to sell it to רב גידל. Rav Gidel. Why
not? דערא קמייתא היא, De'ar'a kamaita hi, it's the first plot of
land I ever bought. ולא מסמנא מילתא, Velo masmana milta, it's not
a good סימן, siman, it's not a good like, you know, it's
an עין הרע ayin hara or something for me to have to,
you know, because apparently like now we would think, you know, you
buy, you sell, whatever, but there, you know, the purchase of buying
land was that you keep it, right? You know, it's not for,
you know, to what's it called, you're not, it's not like buying
a house to turn it over, right? So it's a bad סימן
siman if the, if you're divesting yourself, selling off your property doesn't
look good. You want to be the people that sell off their
property, are people that are really have hit poverty, right? So therefore
to sell property would not be a good thing, especially my first
plot of land that I ever bought. איבעי, Iba'ei, but if you
want, במתנה נישקליה, bematana nishkalei, let him take it as a gift.
Okay? I'll give, I'm happy, I'll happy to give it to him
as a gift. That's not a bad סימן. siman. If you give
away your property it shows you're well off. So רב גידל לא
נחית לה, Rav Gidel lo nachis lah, but רב גידל Rav Gidel
would refuse to go into the land, to take it. דכתיב Dechtiv
ושונא מתנות יחיה. vesonei matanot yichye. I'm not going to take a
gift. Right? The person who hates gifts will live. Who am I?
I need to take gifts from people? No, I want to have
things because I earned them. So רבי אבא Rabbi Abba stayed
by offering it as a gift because he knew he wouldn't take
it?
I don't know, maybe, we don't know, that's already speculation. רבי אבא
לא נחית לה Rabbi Abba lo nachis lah משום דהפיך ביה רב
גידל. mishum dehappeich bei Rav Gidel. רבי אבא Rabbi Abba refused to
use it, wouldn't go down and use the land like נחית, nachis,
go into it, like, you know, take possession of it, because רב
גידל Rav Gidel was trying to have, was trying to purchase it
and he unwittingly took it out from away from רב גידל. Rav
Gidel.
Okay? רב גידל, Rav Gidel, לא מר נחית לה ולא מר נחית
לה. lo mar nachis lah velo mar nachis lah. Neither one was
willing to go into the land. One didn't want to take gifts,
the other didn't want to take it because he because רב גידל
Rav Gidel had been because רב גידל Rav Gidel had been interested
in it. ומתקרי ארעא דרבנן, Umitkarei ar'a derabbanan, it was called the
land of the rabbis because apparently the רש"י Rashi says this, they
basically left it over for the use of the בני ישיבה. benei
yeshiva. Neither of them took possession, it was given over to public
use. Okay? Nice little story about everybody trying to do the right
thing to end a discussion of people doing the wrong thing. Now
by the way, this raises interesting questions about what did he mean
that he was מהפך בחררה. mehappech becharara. What degree of engagement did
he have that it would make it inappropriate to jump in, right?
And this is not a case of being a שליח. shaliach. So
if you take a look, let's look very quickly at a very
interesting תוספות. Tosafot. עני המהפך בחררה, Ani mehappech becharara, תוספות Tosafot says
ובא אחר ונטלה, uva acher venatla, פירוש perush כגון בחררה של הפקר
kegon becharara shel hefker that it was a, it was a... Like
a cake that was ownerless. So you were about to seize something
that was ownerless, and I jumped ahead and I seized it before
you. Because שמהא דתנן בפרק שנים אוחזין, She-me-ha d'tnan be-perek Shnayim Ochazin,
and he says that's difficult because there's other גמרות Gemaras that sound
like when it comes to finding a lost object in the street,
even if you saw it first, if I jumped and grabbed it
first, it's mine. So תוספות Tosafot says if you skip down ואומר
רבינו תם, Ve-omer Rabbeinu Tam, it's about one, two, three, four, about
eight lines down in the narrow lines, the line starts with דאיסורא.
De-issura. דאיסורא דמהפך דניחא ליה הכא לא שייך אלא דוקא כשהוא רוצה
להרוויח בהפקר או כשרוצה לקנות דבר אחד וחברו מקדים וקונה והוי דומיא
דרב גידל ומשום הכי קרי ליה רשע כי למה מחזר על זאת
שטרח בה חברו לילך ולהשתכר במקום אחר אבל אם היתה חררה דהפקר
ליכא איסור שאם לא יזכה בזאת לא ימצא אחרת.
De-issura de-mehapeak de-nicha lei hacha lo shayach ela davka k'she-hu rotze leharviach
be-hefker o k'she-rotze liknot davar echad ve-chavero makdim ve-koneh ve-havei dumya de-Rav
Giddal u-mishum hachi kari lei rasha ki lama mechazer al zot she-tarach
bah chavero leilech u-le-histacher be-makom acher aval
im hayta chararah de-hefker leika issur she-im lo yizkeh be-zot lo yimtzah
acheret. So תוספות Tosafot says, look, if it's a lost object, if
it's a מציאה, Metziah, only one person can get it, there's only
one opportunity to get it. Even if you saw it first, why
should I let you take it? I'm going to take it. I
don't have any other chance to get this lost object. Right? Here
it is, a hundred-dollar bill floating around. Right? Why does the fact
that you see it first entitle you to it? First, you know,
it's whatever. It's every man for himself. But if you're not talking
about something like a מציאה Metziah that, you know, which is what
does they call that? A zero-sum game. Right? If I take, you
know, you take it, I don't get it. I take it, you
don't get it. But if we're talking about a type of a
business arrangement, right, whereas like you're working, you know, to try to
in this case you were trying to buy a plot of land,
he was trying to enter in, this עני Ani was trying to
enter into some type of a business deal that he somebody would
I don't know sell him cakes and then he would go ahead
and, you know, resell them or something like that. So that's a
type of a thing where there are two differences. Number one is
you could say he put in effort, but more relevant for תוספות
Tosafot than the effort issue is that, you know, I've been working
to make this deal, you go ahead and you find another deal
for you to make for yourself. Right? It's not like there's only
one such opportunity. So it becomes very interesting for תוספות, Tosafot, this
idea where you're not a שליח. Shliach. Right? This is the question.
When when you are not a שליח, Shliach, is it inappropriate for
you to like jump in and take something that your friend had
his eye on? Right? And תוספות Tosafot what it says, well, if
I if there's no other opportunity, and by the way, an interesting
case would be this case of marriage. All right? I'm courting a
woman, you know, you see her, you want her, you're going to
jump in and you're going to court her. Right? You could say,
oh, well find a woman for yourself. Like there's only one such
woman, right? Everybody is unique. So like if it's like I can't
like find some opportunity like that for yourself, go do right, then
then, you know, that maybe you do have a right. No, go
back to by the way the first דף Daf in the גמרא
Gemara where it compared the whole idea about finding a woman to
a מציאה. Metziah. Remember that? Where it says like the person who
lost and finding his
מציאה. Metziah. So anyway, who's you know, but but like so when
you're not a שליח, Shliach, are you allowed to just, you know,
totally focus on your own interests, or do you have to care
about what I was engaged in? So for תוספות, Tosafot, it's like
if you can go ahead and put in the effort and find
a similar opportunity yourself, you can't interfere with what I'm doing. But
if you don't have a similar type of an opportunity, it's a
case of a מציאה Metziah or maybe a case, you know, or
you know, something again like I think like marrying this woman where
where we're not dealing with שליחות, Shlichus, then it's like you should
not, you know, then it's like, you know, if if there's a
zero-sum game and you don't have an equal opportunity, maybe it is
every man for himself. All right, but then תוספות Tosafot gets to
this other question about an issue about מיהו קשה. Mihu kasha. Let's
just look at another line because this is just again I think
so so interesting in terms of the, you know, not only הלכתי,
Halachic, but the the ethical questions it raises. מהא דבפרק לא יחפור
דאמר התם מרחיקין מן הדג כמלא ריצת הדג אף על פי שהוא
של הפקר. Me-ha de-be-perek Lo Yachpor d'amar hatam marchikin min ha-dag ki-melo
ritzat ha-dag af al pi she-hu shel hefker. There basically is I'm
going ahead and I'm casting out a net, and you're not allowed
to start casting nets where I'm casting nets for fishing, even though
the fish don't yet belong to me yet. ויש לומר דהתם היינו
טעמא משום יורד לאומנותו. Ve-yesh lomar de-hatam haynu ta'ama mishum yored le-umanuto.
There it's different because there you're interfering with my business. So here
it makes a different issue, right? If my business is to catch
fish, even if the fish are הפקר, Hefker, we don't look at
it like, oh, it's a מציאה, Metziah, it's a lost object I
saw on the street. I'm setting up my business here. You want
to go ahead and have a similar business, you go find somewhere
else. Right? This is where I got here first. Right? So it
raises all these interesting questions of the difference between grabbing an opportunity
to purchase an object, to take an object, to marry a woman,
where I could sort of say, hey, you know, like you know,
it's like you know go you know go you know go like
I like so that's like that's one taste where תוספות Tosafot says
if I don't own the object yet and I'm not in negotiations
yet or whatever, I can sort of, you know, then you you
have a right to try to seize it for yourself, as opposed
to when I'm sort of engaged in a business and you're interfering
with my business. So let's just skip to the end here where
he has a practical application, and he says like this. He says,
ומכאן נראה
למורינו הרב יצחק שאסור למלמד להשכיר עצמו לבעל הבית שיש לו מלמד
אחר בביתו. U-mikan nira le-morenu ha-rav Yitzchak she-assur le-melamed le-haskir atzmo le-ba'al
ha-bayit she-yesh lo melamed acher be-veito.
Let's say you are you have somebody who you've hired to tutor
your kids, and I'm looking for a job of tutoring, I can't
go... Let's say you have somebody who you've hired to tutor your
kids, and I'm looking for a job of tutoring. I can't go
to you and say, "You know, David, I'm a much better tutor
than that guy you've got. Like, maybe you'd like to hire me."
Okay. Why? Because that guy's already engaged, and I'm interfering with his
existing פרנסה parnassah arrangement, okay?
Right,
then also the point being again like go somewhere else, right? So
אם
לא im lo
that the owner says, if the homeowner says, "You know what, I'm
not so happy with my current employee and I'm looking for somebody
to take the position," then of course you can compete for the
position. ואם שכר בעל הבית מלמד אחד, ve'im sachar ba'al habayis melamed
echad,
but let's say I've hired a certain teacher, יכול בעל הבית אחר
לשכור אותו מלמד לעצמו, yachol ba'al habayis acher liskor oso melamed le'atzmo,
somebody else can hire him away from me. Now, why isn't that
like stealing? You're stealing my employee, you're stealing the plot of land
that I was trying to buy? So why is that different? Why
is that okay? ואינו יכול לומר לו בעל הבית לך ושכור מלמד
אחר, ve'eino yachol lomar lo ba'al habayis lech uschar melamed acher, "Go
find somebody else, this is my employee." כי יאמר אינו רצוני אלא
לזה, ki yomar eino ritzoni ela lazeh, because he says, "It's not
my will except for this one," שכן נדמה לי שזה יחכים בני
ממלמד אחר. sheken nidmeh li shezeh yachkim beni mimelamed acher.
No,
he seems to me to be the best one for my son.
I can't, there's no equivalent, which is similar to the idea of
don't tell me to find another woman to marry, this is the
woman I want to marry. So basically according to תוספות, Tosafot, very
interesting, right? When you're given an agency to do something, to go
ahead and do it for yourself is much more dastardly. But if
you're not given the agency and somebody's engaged in something and you're
going to swoop in and take it away, right? So there תוספות
Tosafot basically says that's really fundamentally problematic when the guy had other
opportunities. You could have just as easily gone somewhere else or even
not just as easily, but you could have reasonably found a similar
opportunity for yourself. Okay? But if you could not reasonably have found
a similar opportunity for yourself, like no, I want that teacher that
you've got and I'm willing to pay him more and I'm going
to hire him away from me, I want that woman that you're
courting and there's no other woman that's like that woman, right? So
in that type of a case it actually, you know, would be
appropriate, you're able to act in your own interests. So a really
interesting sort of balancing, you know, those types of cases when you're
a שליח shaliach and when you're not a שליח shaliach and when
like, you know, you're allowed to act in your own interests and
when it's considered to be like a dastardly thing to be doing.
Yes.
It's so problematic, I can't even begin to say.
Like all these years, like I used to watch I was always
responsible for hiring faculty. I never called another school when I knew
that the faculty person had already made an arrangement with the school
to continue the following year. Like, come to us, like, I really
could use I could really use
you, I'll offer what are you getting paid? Right, right. I never
did that ever. Right. And it was like unbelievable, he's saying you
can do that. Right. I find that so problematic.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean I think that there's a
I think that there's a different
That's another factor, right?
Like here that's totally ignored, right? The relationship between the two schools.
Exactly next month I'm going to call the same מנהל. menahel. Right.
And say like, "Listen, I want to talk to you about some
share problems we have." Right, right.
Stay away from my faculty. Right. So that's a practical reason, but
I also think there's a difference between, you know, when they talk
about hiring a מלמד melamed that was much more a think about
it more like I've I mean I don't know enough about the
reality, you know, when תוספות Tosafot was talking about it, but it
was not the same type of a thing of like, you know,
what you think like this is my employee, like the person here
he has an annual salary, they've got benefits, they've got whatever. So
there it's ממש mamash like, you know, it's ממש mamash like taking
something away, right? It's not like these things. It was like before
I think that תוספות Tosafot case is let's say you had a
tutor, right? You had a tutor, for you know, you saw somebody
who was tutoring someone else's kids, right? You know, would you feel
the same issue about saying to them you know what like this
guy would be so good for my kids let me see if
I can. I don't know, it's interesting. It's not the same it's
a little it's a little different when it's more when it's not
as much of like it's already
like how how existing is the current or strong is the current
relationship, you know?
Yeah, I presume we're going to be talking about this in the
next מסכת, masechet, but this comes up all the time in competitive
businesses. There's seven medical schools in New York City and we're stealing
faculty from each other all the time.
Right, there you go.
I have never tried to do it with someone who wasn't already
unhappy and looking around. Right, right. But I have done it with
people who were unhappy and tried to get out. Right. Right.
And then there's this middle ground where you say, "You know, if
you ever want to think about switching places, you should come and
talk to me." Right, right.
Anyway, look, I put that's why I wanted to read this because
it raises those interesting questions. You go from being an agent, right,
which you know and again I think it's interesting because you're still
talking about finding a life partner, so you know what you know
when does that have to trump, you know, the existing relationship that
you've already made and you know again maybe like we said the
גמרא Gemara could be talking about that the guys had a specific
woman, not any woman, maybe already had a relationship with her, maybe
the גמרא Gemara wasn't dealing with this whole issue
of
romantic. But anyway, to cases where you don't have an existing relationship
and it's just going in and grabbing a plot of land and
all these types of cases in between. All right, yes, we have,
we do have to move on.
זה יורד לאומנותו של חברו Ze yored l'umanuto shel chaveiro is the
same as השגת גבול?
Hasagat gevul?
Not exactly, but similar, similar. Okay, yeah, השגת גבול. Hasagat gevul.
Relationship between how close the ties are between two people involved and
how much is this a sense of responsibility? Right. I think in
תענית Ta'anit they talk about the blessings of rain and they say
one of the reasons why we get the blessing of rain is
because of faithfulness between man and man. And I'm kind of thinking
of that.
Right, right, it's a good point, right, exactly, about that sense of
that relationship. Okay. All right. All right, so let's move on, right?
So the משנה Mishnah says like this: וכן
אומר
לאשה התקדשי לי. Vecheyn omer l'ishah hitkadshi li. Okay, so now we
get, we get from the ethical discussion back to the halachic discussion.
So a man says to a woman, marry me, and after thirty
days, and somebody comes and marries her before that time, she's married
to the second guy. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא בא אחר
וקידשה בתוך שלושים מהו? Lo ba acher vekiddesha betoch shloshim mahu? If
a guy didn't marry her within thirty days, what's the story? So
obviously she's married to the first guy after thirty days, but it's
not so obvious. רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו מקודשת, Rav u'Shmuel d'amri tarvayhu
mekudeshet, she's married to the first guy, the only guy, ואף על
פי שנתאכלו המעות. ve'af al pi shenit'achlu hama'ot. But here's their חידוש.
chiddush. Even if the money is no longer around. Now normally if
you do a קניין kinyan that takes effect after time, like after
a certain period of time, you have to have some remnant of
that act of קניין kinyan present after the thirty days. So if
I, for example, say, take my I'm going to buy your cow
and I will own it after thirty days, and I draw the
cow into my property. If at the end of thirty days that
cow is roaming around in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, I don't own
it. When that day thirty comes and my, the קניין kinyan takes
effect, there has to be some thing, some remnant of that original
act of possession that's still present. So if the cow's in my
property, it works. But if the cow is roaming around in רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, it doesn't work. So here they say it works
even if the money is not around. Okay. Now, why is that?
ואף על פי שנתאכלו המעות, ve'af al pi shenit'achlu hama'ot, even if
the money has been consumed. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
הני זוזי לאו למלוה דמו ולאו לפיקדון דמו. Hanei zuzei lav l'milveh
damu v'lav l'pikadon damu. When the money was given, the ring was
given, and said לאחר שלושים יום, le'achar shloshim yom, it's not a
loan and it's not an object for safekeeping. Okay. לפיקדון לא דמו,
Lepikadon lo damu, it's not just an object of safekeeping. Because if
it were an object of safekeeping, it was a פיקדון. pikadon. If
I said, hold on to this money and after thirty days you'll
be married to me with this money. So then if the money
isn't around after thirty days, she's not married, right? Because there's no
money left. But it wasn't a פיקדון. pikadon. How do you know
it wasn't a פיקדון? pikadon? Because if I said hold on to
this money, פיקדון ברשותא דמרא קא מיתכלי. pikadon birshuta d'mara ka mitchali.
If I said hold on to the money and something had happened
to the money, it would have been my loss. I'm giving it
to the woman, hold on to the money, it's still my money,
it would have been my loss. והני ברשותא דידה קא מיתכלי. V'hanei
birshuta didah ka mitchali. Here,
if the money is lost, it's the woman's loss. She's already taken
possession of the money. Okay. So therefore it is not like a
פיקדון. pikadon. Now, it's not a פיקדון, pikadon, so what's, what else
was it? Well, is it a loan? If it were a loan,
it also won't work, because I can't marry a woman with a
loan with money, right? So למלוה נמי לא דמו, L'milveh nami lo
damu, it's not a loan. מלוה להוצאה ניתנה. Milveh l'hotza'ah nitnah. הני
בתורת קידושין יהבינהו ניהלה. Hanei betorat kiddushin yahavin'hu nihala. The purpose of
a loan is that she can go ahead and spend it on
herself and then she'll have to pay me back the money. But
this was given to her not as a loan, but as a
type of a קידושין. kiddushin. Now, what does that all mean? It's
a little complicated, but what it's basically saying is the following is:
If I had said to the woman, hold on to this money
for me and you'll be married to me, it's my money, but
you'll be married to me with it after thirty days, some of
it would have to be around after thirty days, right? Because if
none of it is around, there's nothing left for me to marry
her with. If I said, here is, here's some money, I'm giving
it to you as a loan, and then after thirty days I
said, oh, you know that money you owe me, that hundred dollars
you owe me, you're married to me with it. Okay. I can't
do that because I can't be מקדש במלוה. mekadesh b'milveh. There's nothing
to marry her with. So what it's saying is, but it's neither
of those. Because what it was was, it was money I gave
her and at the time I gave it to her, it was
כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. I didn't say just hold on to this,
it's my money. I didn't say here's a loan. I said, this
is a ring, I'm marrying you with this, this is כסף קידושין.
kesef kiddushin. It'll take effect later. So because that's what I'm saying,
so because it's not a פיקדון pikadon and it's not a loan,
I don't need the thing around then, because essentially it's a long
way for the גמרא Gemara to say because I already gave her
the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin later. I don't need there to be
כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin later, right? Because it was already given to
her originally as a type of a כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. Okay.
If I only focused on the later, on the later I would
either have a פיקדון pikadon that didn't exist or a loan and
I can't marry her with a non-existent פיקדון pikadon and I can't
marry her with a loan. But I don't have either of those.
I actually have the money that I gave her and therefore I'm
able to marry her with it. Now, that doesn't, because of that
original money it was given as כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. Now the
thing is it doesn't really fully answer the question because then just
say right away what's the חידוש? chiddush? You already gave it. the
ring, of course you can marry her, you gave her the ring
30 days ago. But it seems that the point is, like I
said before, that if the original act of the קידוש kiddush of
the transaction is completely
no longer present, right, its memory has been erased, then doesn't take
effect. If I took your cow and 30 days from now it's
roaming in the רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim, there's no remnant of that
original act, its memory has been erased, then it doesn't take effect
30 days from now. But here the memory of it has not
been erased because if she's not married, right, if the marriage doesn't
go through, she's going to have to give the ring back. She's
going to have to give the money back. So there's still a
reality of that transaction, right? She still has the money she took
from that
transaction and if somehow there wouldn't be the transaction, the money would
have
to go back, that money is still by her, is still somehow
in her possession.
But nevertheless 30 days go by and nothing
was done as it were. Well, let's say one of them changed
their mind before the end of the 30 days then the money
would have to go back, right? But in this case 30 days
went by and nothing happened. So it's a complicated way for the
גמרא Gemara to say on the one hand you're not marrying her
with the money after 30 days because there's no money after 30
days to marry her with. There's either a loan or there's nothing,
it doesn't work. You're marrying her with the money you gave her
before. Okay? But normally you need some remnant of that act to
still be present. The sort of remnant of the act is that
she still has that money that she received and she'd otherwise have
to give it back, okay, but that's enough to create that the
first act is still considered to be present, but you're marrying her
with the initial money, not with anything later on. Later on there
isn't the money to marry her with. All right, let's continue. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. לא בא אחר וקידשה וחזרה
בה מהו? Lo ba acher vekiddesha vechazrah bah mahu?
Now let's say somebody did not marry her in 30 days and
she changed her mind before the 30 days were up. So when
you say after 30 days, would that presumably mean that there's some
opportunity to back out? Not only does it not take effect, but
if it doesn't take effect you could presumably back out within that
period of time. So what's the הלכה halacha if she changed her
mind? רבי יוחנן אומר חוזרת, Rabbi Yochanan omer chozeres, she can change
her mind. אתי דיבור ומבטל דיבור, Asi dibbur umevatel dibbur,
her word negates the word. Meaning until now it's seen as only
not yet the act of קידושין, kiddushin, just the word of קידושין,
kiddushin, because it hasn't taken effect yet. So she can therefore reverse
that and negate that by saying she's backing out. וריש לקיש אמר
אינה חוזרת, VeResh Lakish amar einah chozeres, she cannot back out. לא
אתי דיבור ומבטל מעשה. Lo asi dibbur umevatel maaseh. No, it doesn't
negate it. איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש, Eiseivei Rabbi Yochanan leResh Lakish,
איתיביה. Eiseivei. ביטל. Bitel.
Let's say I made a שליח shaliach to take תרומה terumah for
me and then I voided the שליחות. shlichus. אם עד שלא תרם
ביטל, Im ad shelo saram bitel, if I voided it before he
took the תרומה, terumah, אין תרומתו תרומה. ein trumaso trumah. It's not
good. So you see you can void a שליחות. shlichus. והכא דדיבור
ודיבור הוא, Vehacha dedibbur vedibbur hu, I made him a שליח shaliach
through my words, I voided it through my words, ואתי דיבור ומבטל
דיבור, ve'asi dibbur umevatel dibbur, and the second and the voiding negated
the first appointing of שליחות. shlichus. So here too the voiding should
negate the act of קידושין. kiddushin. But he says no, שאני נתינת
מעות לידי אשה דכמעשה דמי. Shani nesinas maos liyadei ishah dechemaaseh dami.
When you and here
there was actually an act. It wasn't all words. Money was given
into this woman's hands. So since money was given into this woman's
hands, yes it hasn't taken effect yet, but that's seen as an
act and the just words to say I back out is not
enough to reverse that act. Okay? So now ולא אתי דיבור ומבטל
מעשה, vilo asi dibbur umevatel maaseh, and words cannot negate the act.
That's ריש לקיש'ס Resh Lakish's position. איתיביה, Eiseivei, I'll ask you. השולח
גט לאשתו והגיע בשליח. Hasholeach get le'ishto vehiga bishaliach.
We had this in גיטין. Gittin. A man sends a messenger to
deliver a גט get to his wife. או ששלח שליח אחר שליח,
O sheshalach shaliach acher shaliach, or
he sent a messenger after him. ואמר לו, Ve'amar lo, and said
to him, גט שנתתי לך בטל, get shenasasi lecha batel, the גט
get I've given you is voided, הרי זה בטל, harei ze batel,
it's voided. Okay? Now there's a whole question are you voiding the
גט get or voiding the שליחות? shlichus? We're going to focus on
voiding the שליחות. shlichus. Okay? ונתינת גט ליד שליח דכנתינת מעות לידי
אשה דמי, Venisinas get leyad shaliach dichenisinas maos liyadei ishah dami, it's
exactly parallel. Give money to the woman, give the ring to the
woman, give the גט get to the שליח shaliach and if you
can your words can void the giving of the גט get to
the שליח, shaliach, it could void your giving of the money to
the woman or her words can void that. Okay? וקתני הרי זה
בטל, Vekasani harei ze batel, and you're able to negate the שליחות.
shlichus. So he says no, התם נמי כל כמה דלא מטא גיטא
לידה, Hasam nami kol kamma dila mata gitta leyadah, no,
no, no, there also, even though there was a physical גט get
that was given, as long as the גט get did not reach
her hand, דיבור הוא, dibbur hu, it's only words. Meaning the act
of גירושין gerushin has not taken effect. Right? A גט get was
given to a שליח, shaliach, there was a physical act, but it
wasn't the act of delivering the גט, get, it wasn't the act
of גירושין. gerushin. So therefore before the actual act that effects the
whole status change took effect, then something is still abstract, it hasn't
yet become concretized, and it can be negated. ודיבור הוא, Vedibbur hu,
it's words, ואתי דיבור ומבטל דיבור. ve'asi dibbur umevatel dibbur. But when
you give the ring that is the act of קידושין. kiddushin. So
it's true the קידושין kiddushin didn't take effect, but the act of
קידושין kiddushin was done. And once the act of קידושין kiddushin was
done, words cannot negate the act. Maybe something else could, I don't
know, if you throw the ring back in his face, it's not
clear, but simple words cannot negate it once the actual act has
been done. That's ריש לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's position. איתיבי ריש לקיש לרבי
יוחנן. Eisiv Reish Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan. Now ריש לקיש Reish Lakish challenged
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. כל הכלים יורדים לידי טומאתן במחשבה. Kol hakelim
yordim lidei tumatan b'machshava. All vessels can become fit to become receptable
for טומאה, tumah, susceptible for טומאה, tumah, something is only susceptible for
טומאה tumah when you're making a vessel, when you're done making it.
Now how do you know when you're done? Right here you are,
you're fashioning a nice bowl. Are you done making the bowl? Do
you still have to polish it? You want to make a little
design on it? At what stage are you done? Okay? So your
thought is enough to determine that you're done. You made the bowl
and you said you thought initially you were in the middle and
then you said it's fine as it is. As soon as you
think it's fine as it is, I'm done, now it's considered a
bowl and now it can become it's become טמא. tamei. ואין עולים
מידי טומאתן אלא בשינוי מעשה. V'ein olim midei tumatan ela b'shinuy maaseh.
But after you've made that decision, I'm done, then you can say
it came to my mind, I want to go ahead and make
a little finish it off and gloss it off and make a
little a little design on it. That's not enough to make it
yet now not a bowl. Once you've decided you're done and it's
a bowl and it's a vessel, the only thing that now makes
it not a finished vessel is if you actually start going in
and working on it again. You actually go ahead and start carving
it and shining it, but just thinking I want to do something
more to it, once it got the status of a vessel with
your thought, it doesn't lose that status just through your thought. You
would need an act to reverse that status.
This is really interesting. No, this is kind of
thought, language, and action and the interrelationship for status and identity.
Right, of course, again there seems to be a huge difference between
first of all the bowl was initially made through your action, so
it was an interaction of thought and action defining when your process
is done and it seems very very different from this question of
when you did a legal act and are you still able to
void it and what you need to void a legal act. Here
it's a question
about whether you're still in the middle of the process of making
the vessel or not. Like to me it seems big differences. They're
all both of them are fascinating. Anyway, the end of the משנה
mishna is: מעשה מוציא מיד מעשה, Maaseh motzi miyad maaseh,
an act can reverse an act. If you did a מעשה maaseh
and you shined it and showed you were done, but then you
go back and you continue working on it, so then it's not
yet a done vessel. ומיד מחשבה, U'miyad machshava, and certainly if you
go ahead and back work on it again after having thought it's
done, then that shows that it's not yet done. מחשבה, Machshava, but
just a thought, אין מוציא לא מיד מעשה, ein motzi lo miyad
maaseh, cannot reverse an act. If you did some type of a
shining and polishing and then you think I want to go back,
obviously that's not enough. But not only that, ולא מיד מחשבה, v'lo
miyad machshava, even if you just thought you were done and then
you changed your mind, it still is considered done until you do
something. So you see, בשלמא מיד מעשה לא מפקא, bishlama miyad maaseh
lo mafka,
clearly your thought doesn't reverse an act, דלא אתי דיבור ומבטל מעשה,
d'lo ati dibbur mevattel maaseh, words don't reverse an act. אלא מיד
מחשבה מי תפקה? Ela miyad machshava mi tesei? Let it go reverse
your thought. So according to you רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, if words
can reverse words, why can't thought reverse a thought by the making
of a vessel? So he says no, שאני מחשבה דטומאה
דכי מעשה דמיא. shani machshava d'tumah d'chi maaseh damya. There's different, because
there's a פסוק pasuk that shows you that when it comes to
טומאה, tumah, your thought is like an action
when it makes something susceptible for טומאה. tumah. Okay, וכדרב פפא. u'kh'd'Rav
Pappa. רב פפא רמי: Rav Pappa rami: כתיב, Ksiv, כי יתן. Ki
yitten. It says if water is placed on food, on a seed,
it'll be susceptible for טומאה. tumah. דקרינן, Dekarinan, כי יוטן. Ki yutan.
But we read it as not you placed it, if you place
water on food, on a seed, but if water is placed, passively.
הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? So what is it? When does food become
susceptible? Do you have to actively place a liquid on it? So
we say, כי יוטן דומיא דכי יתן. Ki yutan dumya d'ki yitten.
Even if it's placed by itself in a way that's similar to
you actively placing it. מה יתן דניחא ליה, Ma yitten d'nichlei, the
same as if you actively put the water on the seed because
you wanted it, אף יוטן דניחא ליה. af yutan d'nichlei. Even if
it just rained on the seed, but you were happy with it,
you liked it, it's like you placed it. So for the הלכה
halacha that food only becomes susceptible for טומאה tumah when it comes
in contact with water with a liquid, the הלכה halacha is it
doesn't have to be that you placed the liquid, even if it
was accidentally came in contact with liquid as long as it was
you were happy with it, you wanted it. So מחשבה machshava when
you like the כי יוטן ki yutan it becomes like a כי
יתן. ki yitten. So when it comes to making something susceptible for
טומאה, tumah, we say your מחשבה machshava is like an action. So
when you like the water on it, it's like you placed the
water on it, when you've decided the vessel is done, it's like
you did an action to make the vessel done, and because it's
like an action, your thought doesn't negate it. But in other areas,
thought would negate thought and that's רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's position. Again,
he bases it on a פסוק pasuk but to me there's still
a huge difference between saying when do I consider the vessel done,
what's the interaction of process and action and thought as opposed to
when I actually did a legal act. a legal act that hasn't
taken effect yet, am I still in a position to void it?
You know this to me seems like to be hugely different questions.
In the world of טומאה, tumah, it means that things are so
vulnerable to טומאה. tumah. מחשבה machshava is strong enough to make it
susceptible. Okay, yeah.
And this is what we were saying, but this is a big
difference here between like once once the vessel assumes a status that
it can be מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, who says that you can
change that?
Right. So that's actually not exactly what I was saying, but that's
also an excellent point, which is is that the status has already
changed by the vessel. And that's what the גמרא Gemara actually could
have said. What do you mean? Here it's like a מעשה ma'aseh
because it already had a status, it already had a שם כלי,
shem kli, right? When you did a מעשה קידושין, ma'aseh kiddushin, no
status has taken effect yet. That's even a better way of saying
it, which is correct, you know, the status has already changed. Okay,
let's read a little bit. I know it's already 8:30, but we're
just about to read a little bit more. It says like this.
Okay, רב זביד מתני להא שמעתא אהא. Rav Zavid matni leha shemata
aha. רב זביד Rav Zavid taught this discussion not on about whether
דיבור מבטל דיבור, dibbur mevatel dibbur, not on the case of לאחר
שלושים יום, le'achar sheloshim yom, but on another case. וכן היא שנתנה
רשות לשלוחה, vechen hi shenatna reshut lishlucha,
a woman made a representative לקדשה, lekadsha, gave right to a agent
to marry her off. So a woman made an agent to accept
קידושין kiddushin on her behalf. והלכה היא וקידשה עצמה, vehalcha hi vekidska
atzmah, then she went and she married herself off. אם שלה קדמו
קידושיה קידושין, im shelah kadmu kiddusheha kiddushin,
if she married before the שליח shaliach married her off, then
her marriage is binding. ואם של שליח קדמו, ve'im shel shaliach kadmu,
but if her agent married her before she married herself off, אין
קידושיה קידושין, ein kiddusheha kiddushin, then what she did isn't meaningful because
the agent went ahead and did it first on her behalf. Now
the גמרא Gemara asks the question, לא קידשה עצמה, lo kidsha atzmah,
let's say she made this agent, she didn't marry herself off, וחזרה
בה, vechazra bah, and then she said I am retracting my agent.
מהו? mahu? What's the story? רבי יוחנן אמר חוזרת, Rabbi Yochanan amar
chozeret, she can void her agent, וריש לקיש אמר אינה חוזרת, veResh
Lakish amar eina chozeret, she cannot. Now by the way, תוספות Tosafot
says this is crazy. How could you say I can make an
agent and then be yelling and saying I don't want that agent
to act on my behalf and the agent can still go ahead
and marry you off against your wishes? Okay, so תוספות, Tosafot, which
sounds like what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is saying.
Wait, the agent doesn't know that you're yelling and screaming?
Okay, but we know. Okay, so anyway תוספות Tosafot tries to explain
it in its, right? She goes in front of a בית דין
Beis Din and she announces, I sent this guy, I changed my
mind, I don't want him to marry myself off. We say oh
sorry, לא אתי דיבור ומבטל דיבור, lo ati dibbur umevatel dibbur, he
married you, tough luck. Right? It's like crazy. So תוספות Tosafot tries,
let's just go, תוספות Tosafot tries to explain what would be the
case that ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, you know, that he tries to
say that it's not so much that she's refusing, anyway, but ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish sounds very extreme here that you cannot negate your
שליחות shlichut and somebody could represent you against your will. רבי יוחנן
אמר חוזרת, Rabbi Yochanan amar chozeret, אתי דיבור ומבטל דיבור, ati dibbur
umevatel dibbur, your words negate your words. You voided your שליחות. shlichut.
וריש לקיש אמר אינה חוזרת, veResh Lakish amar eina chozeret, לא אתי
דיבור ומבטל דיבור, lo ati dibbur umevatel dibbur, you can't negate your
שליחות, shlichut, which is wild. איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש. Eitiveh Rabbi
Yochanan leResh Lakish. ביטל, bitel, here you negated your שליח shaliach by
תרומה. trumah. You negated your שליח. shaliach. אם עד שלא תרם ביטל
אין תרומתו תרומה. im ad shelo taram bitel ein trumato trumah. So
you see you can negate your שליחות, shlichut, okay, and in both
cases there's no object, it's just words of appointing a שליח. shaliach.
אמר רב לא הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שקדם בעל הבית ותרם מכליו,
Amar Rav lo hacha bemai askinan kegon shekadam ba'al habayit vetaram mikalyav,
דהוה ליה מעשה. dehava leh ma'aseh.
No, the negating is a negating done through an action, right? Because
all these questions is, okay, words can't negate, could there be an
action that could negate? So yes, maybe view the same way how
would a woman negate her שליח? shaliach? She would marry herself off.
How would I negate my שליח shaliach to do תרומה? trumah? I
would take my own תרומה. trumah. So if you did an action
to take repossession, repossess your rights, that would be meaningful, but it
could be your words are not enough. Okay, so we're still, so
that's going to be the claim, you cannot negate your שליחות shlichut
with words, you'd have to do an action. Okay, let's just, we're
going to just go through the same issues. איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש
לקיש. Eitiveh Rabbi Yochanan leResh Lakish. כל הכלים יורדים לידי טומאתן במחשבה,
Kol hakelim yordim lidei tumatan bemachshava, ואין עולים מטומאתן אלא בשינוי מעשה.
ve'ein olim mitumatan ela beshinuy ma'aseh. מעשה מוציא מיד מעשה ומיד מחשבה,
Ma'aseh motzi miyad ma'aseh umiyad machshava, מחשבה אינה מוציאה לא מיד מעשה
ולא מיד מחשבה. machshava eina motzia lo miyad ma'aseh velo miyad machshava.
The same issue with the טומאה. tumah.
So you see words don't negate words. בשלמא מיד מעשה לא מפקיע,
Bishlama miyad ma'aseh lo mafkia, your thought doesn't negate action, לא אתי
דיבור ומבטל מעשה. lo ati dibbur umevatel ma'aseh. אלא מיד מחשבה מיד
תיפוק? Ela miyad machshava miyad tipok? Why don't, why doesn't your thought
negate your thought by the making of the vessel? אמר ליה שאני
מחשבה דטומאה דכי מעשה דמיא כרב פפא. Amar leh shani machshava detumah
dechi ma'aseh damya keRav Pappa. Okay, no, that's different. Thought about טומאה
tumah is like an action. דהא רב פפא רמי, deha Rav Pappa
rami, כתיב כי יותן וקרינן כי יותן. ketiv ki yutan vekarinan ki
yutan. הכיצד? Hakeitzad? כי יותן דומיא דכי יותן. Ki yutan dumya deki
yutan. מה יותן דניחא ליה אף יותן דניחא ליה. Ma yutan denicha
leh af yutan denicha leh. Same thing we said. There when you
think that you want it, it's like you did the act of
placing the liquid on it. And when you think you like the
vessel, it's like you did the act of making the vessel. So
there thought cannot negate the thought because the first thought was like
an action. Now we get to the key point. איתיביה רבי יוחנן
לריש לקיש. Eitiveh Rabbi Yochanan leResh Lakish. השלוח גט לאשתו והגיע בשליח,
Hashaluach get le'ishto vehigia bashaliach, או ששלח אחר השליח, o sheshalach achar
hashaliach, ואמר לו גט שנתתי לך בטל הוא. ve'amar lo get shenatati
lecha batel hu. הרי זה בטל. harei ze batel. So there it's
clear, you sent a שליח, shaliach, you did not do an act,
you just negated your שליח shaliach with words. So you see, you
sent a שליח, shaliach, you can negate your שליח shaliach with words,
right, when you sent your שליח shliach for the גט. get. The
גמרא Gemara says, תיובתא דריש לקיש תיובתא. tiyuvta d'Reish Lakish tiyuvta. That's
a complete contradiction of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish.
Certainly in the second case, if you verbally make a שליח, shaliach,
you can negate your שליח shaliach with words. But the גמרא Gemara
says, והלכתא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן ואפילו בקמייתא, v'hilchosa k'vosei d'Rabbi Yochanan v'afillu
b'kamaisa,
and we rule like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and not only can
your words negate your שליח, shaliach, but your words can even negate
when you say the קידושין kiddushin should take place after thirty days.
There you did an act, you gave the ring to the woman,
and nevertheless, since it hasn't taken effect, you can negate it anytime
before it's taken effect. So we rushed a little bit, but we're
going to pick up on that tomorrow so we can have a
chance to appreciate the bottom line פסק הלכה psak halacha here, that
not only can you negate the appointment of a שליח, shaliach, but
you can actually back out on a transaction that has taken—the act—the
act was done, but the transaction hasn't taken effect yet, and in
that type of a case according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan you
can negate it, that's how we rule, we'll continue to see that
tomorrow.
Did he really ask the...